你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到PWN学院面向返回编程模块的第2个视频
welcome to video 2 of the return oriented programming module of pwn college
标题很奇怪，叫二进制乐高
strangely enough called binary Lego
乐高是什么?
what is Lego
是的，我说的是乐高，就是你用来搭东西的塑料积木
yes I am talking about Lego the plastic blocks with which you build stuff
因为它是面向返回编程的完美比喻
because it is a perfect analogy for return oriented programming
当你拿到一组乐高积木
when you acquire Lego set
它附带了一堆积木和一本说明书
it comes with a bunch of blocks an instruction booklet
按照说明书上的指令操作
by following the instruction booklets instructions
并以特定的方式将积木组合在一起
and putting blocks together in a specific way
你能创造一个东西，比如乐高汽车
you create a Lego structure like a car
然后呢
now what happens
如果你离开房间
if you leave the room
你的室友、兄弟姐妹或者对手跑了进来
and your roommate sibling adversary runs in
在你的乐高说明书上乱改一通
and scribbles all over your Lego instruction booklet
你回来了
you come back
你没有注意到
you don't notice
你继续建造
and you keep building
如果你遵循一个恶意制作的乐高说明书
if you follow a maliciously crafted lego instruction booklet
用同样的乐高积木
with the same Lego pieces
你会建造一些完全不同的东西
you could build something completely different
一些和你想的完全不同的东西
something that will blow up your plans
因为它们是专门恶意制作
because they're specifically maliciously crafted
来实现一个不同于原来乐高指令的目标
to achieve a different goal than the original lego instructions
这是面向返回的编程的比喻
this is the analogy of return oriented programming
在这个比喻中，积木块是二进制文件text段中的字节
in this analogy the blocks are bytes in the text section of your binary
也就是可执行数据
executable data
说明书是
the instruction book that is the
存储着可被溢出覆盖的函数返回地址的栈
stack with its stored return addresses that can be overwritten by a stack based overflow
遵照指示努力的结果
and the result of the effort of following the instructions
是程序采取的行动
are the actions taken by the program
通过覆盖返回地址，额，覆盖栈，额
and by overwriting the return address umm overwriting the stack
覆盖存储的返回地址
overwriting store to return addresses
攻击者可以强制CPU
the attacker can force the CPU
用这些积木
to take those blocks
text段中的原始字节
the raw bytes in the text segment
把它们构建成不同的东西
and build them into something different
一些本没打算构建的东西
something that wasn't intended to be built by the program
好，让我们看一下这个类比对应的源代码
all right let's take a look at a conceptual analogy on source code
然后会深入研究
and then I'll actually dive in
并在二进制级别上进行这种攻击
and do this exact attack that I'm talking about on binary level
这是一个要求你输入名字的程序，仅此而已
here's a program that asks for your name and that's it
它还碰巧在二进制文件中有打开flag文件的代码
it also happens to have code in the binary that will open the flag file
但没有读写flag
do nothing with it
它还有代码是打开其它文件
it also has code in the binary that will open something that is not the flag file
然后输出文件内容
and send you the output
这些都不能让你得到flag
right none of this quite gets you the flag
但这里也存在一些问题
but there are problems here
最明显的是缓冲区溢出
the obvious one is a buffer overflow
可以用它覆盖返回地址
with which you can overwrite the return address
你不仅可以覆盖返回地址
and you can overwrite not just the return address
还可以覆盖返回地址之后的数据
but the data address after that return address
通常，该数据可能包含libc_start_main的栈局部变量（被调是main）
normally that data might contain stack local variables of libc_start_main
或者其它情况（不同c运行环境等）的主调函数
or what have you
但这不是必须的
right but it doesn't have to
一旦你溢出覆盖了它，栈就不记得之前它是什么了
the stack has no memory of what it used to be once you overflow it
一旦溢出并触发第一次返回
once you overflow it and trigger that 1st return
程序将按照您的指示继续运行
your program continues according to your instructions
你已经重写了乐高手册
you have overwritten the Lego manual
手册不再记得在一个特定的步骤中涉及多少个部件
the manual no longer remembers how many pieces are involved in one specific step
原来返回地址指向哪里已经无所谓了
where the return addresses used to be is irrelevant
重要的是现在栈上有什么
what's relevant is what is on the stack and
这将告诉CPU要做什么
what that is telling the CPU to do
我们先看幻灯片上的这个然后再看一个实际的例子
so let's take a look at this 1st on the slide and then in an actual example
在幻灯片上我们用a覆盖了16字节的name
on the slide we override you know the name 16 bytes with a
然后是这个返回地址
and then we have this return address
我们用第6行的地址重写它
and we override it with line 6
所以当main返回时
right and so when main returns
它将返回到打开flag文件的这一行，然后返回
it will return into this line that opens the flag file and then returns
当它返回时，它将跳转到第10行
and when this returns it will jump into line 10
这将发送一个文件
that will send a file
某个文件描述符，到标准输出
some file descriptor into a standard out
从文件中的位置0到位置1024
from location 0 to location 1024 in that file
我们的标准打开发送文件shellcode
our standard open send file shellcode
通过精心制作返回地址
by crafting return addresses carefully
我们成功执行了打开发送文件shellcode
we've managed to essentially execute what is the open send file shellcode
通过ROP
using return oriented programming
我们来实际做一下，看一下
so let's actually do it let's take a look
我创建了rop-example.c
I actually created rop-example.c
这里很神奇
here it is amazing
让我们来编译它
let's compile it
实际上我已经写了这个命令
I already in fact wrote the command
你会立刻注意到的两件事
2 things that you will immediately notice
我们必须禁用栈金丝雀
we have to disable stack canaries
这样我们在溢出的情况下不会被强制退出
so that we can survive the overflow here
我们必须禁用地址空间布局随机化，只针对二进制本身
and we have to disable address space layout randomization just for the binary itself
这对这个简单的例子来说也是很重要的
that's also an important piece for this simple example right
但是在这个模块的习题中
but in your in the practice problems for the module
有些题目是不禁用的
you will have examples where that is not disable
好了，我们编译
alright so we compile this
运行它
and we run it
当然，它不打印任何东西，它只是接收名字
and of course it doesn't print anything it just takes the name
如果我们给它超过16个字节，它就会出现段错误
if we give it more than 16 bytes it'll SEG fault
如果我们GDB并运行
if we gdb and run
然后给它超过16个字节
and then give it more than 16 bytes
它会在返回时出现段错误
it'll SEG fault on the ret
你可以看到它已经溢出了
and you can see that that is overflowed
这说得通，然后
that makes sense and then
下一个数据字节也被溢出
the next data bytes are also overflowed
我输入了相当多
I gave it quite a lot right
好吧
alright
让我们开始ROP
let's ROP
所以
so
首先
1st
让我们
let's
反汇编 rop_example
disassemble the ROP example
有几件事
and there's a couple of things
是我们感兴趣的
that we are interested in
第一，这是main
1st here's main
这是read
here's the read
我们可以看到栈帧的大小是16字节
we can see that the stack frame is 16 bytes in size
然后是保存的RBP，保存的基指针
and then there is the saved RBP the saved base pointer
然后是保存的返回地址
and then the saved return address
对于溢出，我们需要发送16个填充字节
so for the overflow we need to send 16 padding bytes whatever is
然后还有8个字节放入保存在栈上的RBP
then 8 more to that'll get put into RBP
接下来的8个字节是返回地址
and then the next 8 is gonna be the return address
很好，我们对这个程序有两件事很感兴趣
cool and then there are the 2 things that we were interested in in the program
一个在函数foo中
one is in function foo
在函数foo中，它将加载一些东西到RDI中
and in function foo it will load something into RDI
我们当然知道这是/flag
of course we know so that this is slash flag
然后，对了
then it will alright
在那之前，它会将RSI归零
before that it'll zero out RSI
这是打开它的模式
that's the mode to open it with
0是只读
0 is read only
这很好，然后它就会调用open
that's great  and then it'll call open
然后返回
and then it'll return
当然，open会将文件描述符放入RAX中
of course open puts the file descriptor into RAX
现在我们在RAX中有了目标文件描述符
so now we have the file descriptor in RAX
我们弹栈
we pop something off the stack
所以我们发送中的这部分会被重新填到rbp中
so you just send something to be popped again into RBP
然后返回
and we return
当然，我们想跳到bar函数
all right of course we want to then return to bar
在那里sendfile被调用
where we have our sendfile call
如果我们在sendfile调用处往上看
and if we go back upwards from the sendfile call
我们可以看到sendfile
we can see that send file
第一个参数被设置为1
the 1st argument is set to one
它会发送到标准输出
it's going to send to standard output
第二个参数
the 2nd argument
我们非常幸运，它被设置为EAX
we've got very lucky is set to EAX
RAX的低32位
the lower 32 bits of RAX
foo把文件描述符放在那里
which is where foo put the file descriptor
它是完美的，然后第三个参数是0
it's perfect and then 3rd argument is 0
第四个参数是十六进制400，也就是1024
4th argument is hex 400 that is 10 24
所以基本上如果你跳到这里
so basically if you jump here
我们将设置4个参数来发送文件，然后调用它
we'll set the 4 arguments to send file and then call it
一个计划应运而生
a plan comes together
让我们进入screen会话
so let's jump into a screen session
因为我们将从pwntools运行GDB
because we'll run GDB from pwntools um
所以
so
让我们创建一个脚本
let's create a script
不好意思
excuse me um
启动rop-example
will be a launch rop example
然后
and then
然后我们会给它发送一
and then we're going to send it a
一堆数据
a bunch of data
首先我们要发送16个A
1st we're going to send our 16 A's
这是name变量
that's our name
然后我们要发送
then we're going to send
好吧，我们在这里添加注释
so we can say okay let's let's add comments here
这是我们要填充的name
this is our name that we will fill up
然后重写保存的main的基指针
then we overwrite the saved base pointer of main
好了，或者说在main的栈帧中
okay or in main in main's stack frame
好了，现在我们覆盖保存的返回地址
alright then now we are overwriting the saved return address
我们想用什么来覆盖它
what do we want to override it with
我们想用
we want to override it with
bar中的这个地址重写它
this address  right here in bar
我们要从main直接跳到这里
from main we want to immediately jump into here
这是一个加载，哦，这里
this is a load oh into here
这会将open的第二个参数设置为0
this sets the 2nd argument to 0 for open
/flag作为第一个参数
the 1st argument to slash flag
我们假设是/flag
um we're assuming that slash flag
但是我们已经看到了源代码
but we've seen the source code
它就是
um and it is
所以我们想要跳到这里
so we want to jump here
这很好
right so this is nice
这里我们当然会
so here we will of course
将其打包成8个字节
pack that into 8 bytes
好的，现在呢?
okay now what
现在我们跳过去
now we jump there oops
我们跳过去，那很好
we'll jump there and that's great
我们将开始执行
we will start executing
最终我们会弹出栈顶数据填充到RBP
eventually we'll pop RBP
所以我们在写的时候需要在栈上放一些东西
right so we need to put something on the stack as we're writing right
这将会出现在RBP中
that will get popped into RBP so
保存返回地址，我们让他指向foo中的open调用
save return address let's just put in to point to foo's open call
当然还有调用前的设置
and setup of course
现在这个会被Foo弹出
now this is going to get popped by Foo
在返回之前注入RBP
into RBP before it returns
我们就放一些垃圾
so we'll just put some garbage
我们不关心这是什么
we don't care what this is
好吧
okay
现在呢?
now what now this
这是foo返回的位置
this is where foo will return to
那么你想从foo返回到哪里
so where do you want to return to from foo
当然，我们想回到这段漂亮的代码
of course we want to return to this beautiful piece of code
这将设置sendfile调用并调用它
that will set up the sendfile call and call it
我们想回到这里
we want to return to here
所以我们想
so we want to do
返回sendfile调用并在bar中设置
return to the sendfile call and set up in bar
我们在这里打包
and we pack it here
就好了
and we should be good
然后我们调用p.readall
and then we p.readall
打印出来
print it
首发。启动有效载荷。得到flag
1st shot. rock payload. gets the flag
让我们更深入地看看发生了什么
let's see what happens more in depth
执行p.gdb.呃
let's do this p.gdb. uh
pwn.gdb.attach (p)
pwn.gdb.attach(p)
好的，让我们运行到main
okay let's run until main
好了，开始吧
okay here we go
为什么它已经从main返回了
why is it already returning from main
为什么我们到main里这么多了
why are we so far into main
好吧，有点奇怪
okay something went weird
我们，我们开始吧
let's uh let's do this
已经成功了
it all all already succeeded
好吧，我们再来一次
alright let's do this again
现在在read中
and here we are in read
哦，有趣的是，它没有
oh interesting it did not
pwntools做
pwntools did
pwntools只在read时捕获程序
okay so pwntools only caught the program at the read
没关系，没问题
that's fine not a problem
这是有道理的
that actually makes sense
因为它是在事后重新附加上的
because it reattached after the fact
好了，我们完成了读取和溢出操作
okay so we did our read we did our overflow
我们进入read
let's step step into the read
让我们看看我们要回到哪里
let's see where we're about to return to
等等
actually hold on
很抱歉
sorry about this
让我们重新开始，我想向你们展示我们溢出了
let's restart I want to show you that we overflowed
我们成功溢出了
boom we overflowed
看看栈上有什么
let's see what's on the stack
一堆a
a bunch of A's
好了，我们离开这个
okay once we leave that
回退到前一个栈帧
restores the previous stack frame
The The
the the the
它将RBP赋值到RSP中以消除或释放
it moves RBP into RSP to eliminate to deallocate
现有函数栈帧
the existing functions stack frame
然后弹出保存的RBP值到rbp
and then it pops RBP
来恢复上一个函数的基指针
to restore the base pointer the previous function
当然我们重写了RBP
of course we overwrote RBP
RBP现在全是B
RBP is now B all b's
好，如果我们看看接下来是什么
okay if we look at what is next
是我们写的那个地址
it's that address we wrote
这是foo中的地址
this is the address in foo
如果我们继续 boom
if we step boom
我们正在foo中准备调用open
we are in foo setting up the open call
我们开始设置好open调用
let's set up the open call
好的，调用。open被调用
alright call. open has been called
Rax现在是3。第4个文件描述符
Rax is now 3. 3rd file descriptor
我们将在foo栈帧释放中弹出RBP
and we're about to pop RBP and in foo's function cleanup
rbp变成了全c
that's gonna go become all C's
RBP的值无关紧要
RBP doesn't really matter what values are in there
我们只是确认一下
we just need to make sure
我们正确地设置了栈
that we are properly setting up the stack
如果你把返回地址写在这里
if you had put our return I just wrote there
它会被填充到rbp中
would have been popped into RBP
然后程序会跳到一些垃圾中
and then the program would have returned to some garbage
这样就不好了
so that would have been no good
好吧
all right and um
我们将来到利用的下一部分，也就是bar函数
we're about to return to the next part of our exploits  which is in bar
boom，我们到了bar函数
boom here we are in bar
这是sendfile调用前的设置
and this is the setup of sendfile
现在我们要调用sendfile
and we're now about to call send file
和
and
最终程序崩溃
eventually the program crashes
因为我们之后没有费心去修复栈
because we didn't bother fixing up the stack afterwards
但是我们获得了美丽的flag
but we have our beautiful flag
这就是面向返回编程
all right so that's return oriented programming
简而言之，你看到我们通过劫持它的返回地址来控制程序
you saw we were controlling the program by hijacking its return address in a nutshell
但真正的利用要复杂得多，对吧
but real exploits are more complicated right
首先你溢出了栈
1st you overflow the stack
这是我们将要进行的第0步
a step 0 that we're kind of going to go
我们将过一遍ROP的步骤
kind of going to go through return oriented programming by induction
溢出栈，我们做到了。然后
you overflow the stack we did that
通过控制第一个返回地址
by controlling that 1st return address
触发了所谓的gadget
you trigger what is called a gadget
就是foo被触发的那部分
that part of foo that be triggered
它打开了flag
that opened the flag
它就是gadget
that was a gadget
这是一个比你通常触发的更大的gadget
it's a much bigger gadget than you would normally trigger actually
但它确实是个gadget
but it was a gadget right
通常gadget都是超级小的
normally gadgets are super tiny
你们稍后会讲到它们
you'll talk about them in a bit
只有一条指令，然后返回
just one instruction and then a return
但是当那个gadget返回时
but when that gadget returns
我们还控制该gadget的返回地址
we also control the return address of that gadget
这就是一般步骤
and that is the inductive step
我们可以通过组合这些gadget保持对程序的控制，就像刚刚做的那样
where we retain control by combining these gadgets like we did
用两个gadget
with the 2 gadgets
我们可以实现任意的动作
we can achieve arbitrary actions
这就是链式rop gadget
and that's chain of rop gadgets
我躲起来给你看
I hide myself to show you
这叫做ropchain
that word is called a ropchain
很酷，好吧
very cool all right
最重要的是什么
what's the bottom line
最重要的是
the bottom line is that
这个ropchain基本上就是shellcode
your ropchain is basically shellcode
当你创造了所有这些gadget，而你
when you create all of these gadgets and you
我为这张幻灯片的样子道歉
I apologize for how this slide looks
当你创造了这些gadget
but when you create all of these gadgets and
把它们放在一起
put them all together
您实际上是在创建shellcode
you're essentially creating shellcode
但你能得到的指令很奇怪
but the instructions available to you are really weird
我们使用了2条指令
we use 2 instructions
其中一条指令打开flag文件
one of those instructions open the flag file
或者叫元指令
or meta instructions right
一个gadget打开flag文件
2 gadgets one gadget open the flag file
另一个gadget执行sendfile
the other gadget did sendfile
在黑客术语中，这被称为weird machine
in in hacker terms this is called a weird machine
通过编排返回地址进行ROP
you are programming using return oriented program by writing return addresses
机器指令集无所谓
a machine whose instruction set makes no sense
它是由元指令组成的
it's made up of meta instructions that are
元指令是程序原本的部分
you know parts pieces of what the original program actually wanted to do
我们要把它们拆开
and we're taking them apart
把它们组合成别的东西
putting them together into something else
就像你玩乐高积木一样
like you might do again with a Lego set
实际上还有一个相关的概念叫做意外图灵完备性
there's actually a related concept called accidental Turing completeness
如果你点击这个链接
if you check out this link
或者百度相关概念
or Google for the concept
有很多很多东西都是图灵完备的
there are tons and tons of things that actually turned out to accidentally be Turing complete
《magic:the gathering》这款游戏便是一个很好的例子
a good example is the game magic:the gathering
你可以进行计算
you can make computation
你可以创建一个足够复杂的牌组来执行算法
you can create a deck that is complex enough to actually carry out algorithms
基于游戏规则
through the rules of magic gathering the game
还有很多其他的东西也是意外图灵完备的
and there's a lot of other stuff that are also Turing complete by accident
这是一个与weird machine相关的有趣概念
which is an interesting concept related to these weird machines right
很明显
obviously
《magic the gathering》中的牌组就是一种weird machine
a deck in magic the gathering is quite a weird machine
将程序分开，有针对性的重组，也是如此
but so is pieces of program taken apart and stuff back together carefully in a targeted way
核心要点是，rop是有趣的
the core takeaway though is rop is fun
你是个雕刻家
you are a sculptor
你拿到一个无聊的程序
you're taking a boring program
你看到那个程序什么都没做
you saw that program be started with did nothing
通过利用一个漏洞来拆解这个程序
and by exploiting a vulnerability to break that program apart
然后把它们拼在一起
and crafting it back together
通过在栈上小心构建ropchain
by carefully creating a chain of return addresses on the stack
这导致原始程序的部分
that caused pieces of that original program
执行了最初设计中没有的操作
to perform operetions that it was not originally designed to do
我们正在建造一些新的东西
we are building something new
我们是在程序中展示艺术的雕塑家
we're sculptors exposing the art in the program
我希望当你们在享受模块接下来的内容时能想到这个
that's what I would encourage you to think about as you suffer through the rest of the module
这很有趣
this is fun